<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Oracle | My Programmer's Road]]></title>
  <link href="http://ssledz.github.io/blog/categories/oracle/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ssledz.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-04T16:51:13+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://ssledz.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sławomir Śledź]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oracle Certified Professional, Java SE 8 Programmer 1Z0-809 Exam - Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://ssledz.github.io/blog/2016/05/15/oracle-certified-professional-java-se-8-programmer-1z0-809-exam-review/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-15T19:34:09+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ssledz.github.io/blog/2016/05/15/oracle-certified-professional-java-se-8-programmer-1z0-809-exam-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just after passing <a href="https://education.oracle.com/pls/web_prod-plq-dad/db_pages.getpage?page_id=5001&amp;get_params=p_exam_id:1Z0-808">Java SE 8 Programmer 1Z0-808 Exam</a>
(about that you can read <a href="{% post_url 2016-05-15-oracle-certified-associate-java-se-8-programmer-1z0-808-exam-review %}">here</a>) 
and being impressed by <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23059696-oca?from_search=true&amp;search_version=service">OCA: Oracle Certified Associate Java Se 8 Programmer I Study Guide: Exam 1z0-808</a>,
I decided to buy the newly released <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23650477-ocp">OCP: Oracle Certified Professional Java Se 8 Programmer II Study Guide: Exam 1Z0-809</a>.
It was a really good purchase.</p>

<p>The book is awesome. It has a similar style and feel as the <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23059696-oca?from_search=true&amp;search_version=service">OCA: Oracle Certified Associate Java Se 8 Programmer I Study Guide: Exam 1z0-808</a>.
It covers many new features, in details, introduced in <code>java 8</code>.
I learn a lot about <code>lambda</code>, <code>collection streams</code>, <code>date api</code> 
and so on. I can tell you that this book was worth its money.</p>

<p>It took me almost 4 months to go through this book. To be honest I read
it two times. Same as previously (<a href="{% post_url 2016-05-15-oracle-certified-associate-java-se-8-programmer-1z0-808-exam-review %}">OCA - review</a>) 
I was generally reading the book during my way to work. 
First time I really haven’t paid attention on solving tests. 
I have just gone through the book to better know
<code>java 8</code>. After that I took a few weeks break. When I started solving
test questions I noticed that I had a problem with <code>java API</code>. It is
really annoying that the test exam requires from developer to remember
api. In 2016 we have <code>ides</code>, written mainly for this purpose. Due this
fact I started reading a book again. This time however, 
I have been solving test question just after I read a chapter.</p>

<p>In order to prepare to the final exam I used <a href="https://sybextestbanks.wiley.com/public/">sybex</a>
platform. Due the fact that I bought the book I got an access to this
site where I found 411 test questions divided into 3 sets:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Assessment Test (20) - helps you focus your study to specific objectives</li>
  <li>Chapter Tests (211) - taken from the Review Questions at the end of chapters in the book</li>
  <li>Practice Exam (180) - provided to help you prepare for the certification test</li>
</ul>

<p>Moreover I had an access to the following resources:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Flashcards - help to reinforce your learning and provide last-minute test prep before the exam</li>
  <li>Searchable Glossary - instant access to the key terms you’ll need to know for the exam</li>
  <li>Bonus Appendix - provides additional information about JavaScript with Nashorn, and 
enables you to test your knowledge and understanding of this topic.</li>
</ul>

<p>The exam lasted 150 minutes. At the end of the exam I still haven’t 
answered on the two questions. I can say that the exam was much more 
difficult than the <a href="https://education.oracle.com/pls/web_prod-plq-dad/db_pages.getpage?page_id=5001&amp;get_params=p_exam_id:1Z0-808">Java SE 8 Programmer 1Z0-808 Exam</a>.</p>

<p>After receiving the email that my exam results were available I browsed to 
the <strong>CertView</strong> and it appeared that I scored <code>83%</code>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oracle Certified Associate Java SE 8 Programmer 1Z0-808 Exam - Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://ssledz.github.io/blog/2016/05/15/oracle-certified-associate-java-se-8-programmer-1z0-808-exam-review/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-15T12:01:32+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ssledz.github.io/blog/2016/05/15/oracle-certified-associate-java-se-8-programmer-1z0-808-exam-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After successfully passed <a href="https://education.oracle.com/pls/web_prod-plq-dad/db_pages.getpage?page_id=5001&amp;get_params=p_exam_id:1Z0-808">Java SE 8 Programmer 1Z0-808 Exam</a>
I would like to share my thoughts about the preparation and the exam.</p>

<p>I passed the exam and earn the 
<a href="https://www.youracclaim.com/badges/58fa8011-f1da-4a68-846c-b869ee04012b/public_url">badge</a> 
on Dec 2015 - so almost half year ago (since writing this post). 
Before preparation I was playing already with <code>java 8</code> a little. 
I have written two, maybe three applications which were using some 
new hot features like <code>lambda</code>, <code>default methods</code> and <code>streams</code>.
The whole knowledge how to do this I got mainly from oracle 
tutorials like</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/java/javaOO/lambdaexpressions.html">Lambda Expressions</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/collections/streams/index.html">Aggregate Operations</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/java/IandI/defaultmethods.html">Default Methods</a></li>
</ul>

<p>In spite of my experience as a java programmer I decided to spend some 
time to learn more about <code>java 8</code> to ensure that I would really pass the exam.</p>

<p>My journey I have started with the book: <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23059696-oca?from_search=true&amp;search_version=service">OCA: Oracle Certified Associate Java Se 8 Programmer I Study Guide: Exam 1z0-808</a>.
It took me some time, I think one month, to go through all chapters.
The book I was mainly reading during my way to work in metro, bus or tram.
I can say that I was enjoying reading it though I have already known 
most of the knowledge. It is written with a very simple language. I can say
that this book could be understandable by peoples who speak english in an 
intermediate level. It covers all the topics which can appear on 
an exam. After finishing it I bought the voucher on an exam, taking place 
a week later. I had one whole week to play around <code>java 8</code>, make some
tests and review things read in a book. To practice tests I used 
<a href="https://sybextestbanks.wiley.com/public/">sybex</a> platform. In order to 
get an access to this platform you only need to own a book.</p>

<p>On a site you can find 345 test questions divided into 3 sets</p>

<ul>
  <li>Assessment Test (20) - helps you focus your study to specific objectives</li>
  <li>Chapter Tests (145) - taken from the Review Questions at the end of chapters in the book</li>
  <li>Practice Exam (180) - provided to help you prepare for the certification test
Platform also provides an access to 2 other study tools</li>
  <li>Flashcards - help to reinforce your learning and provide last-minute test prep before the exam</li>
  <li>Searchable Glossary - an instant access to the key terms you’ll need to know for the exam</li>
</ul>

<p>The day before the exam I decided to go sleep early. 
The exam lasted 150 minutes, and I had enough time to
answer on all the questions. They weren’t difficult. I can say
that the questions in a mockup exam from sybex were much harder. For example
if the question was a multiple choice question, in a real exam 
I was informed how many answers I needed to choose, 
in a mockup exam I weren’t.</p>

<p>One hour after the exam I received an email that my exam results were available. 
My score was <code>97%</code>. Regarding the response from <code>Oracle</code> 
I made mistakes in a questions from the following exam objectives:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Define the scope of variables</li>
  <li>Manipulate data using the StringBuilder class and methods</li>
</ul>

<p>It could sound strange that the experienced java developer made 
mistakes from the such basic topics. But believe me that the real 
intention of authors of the test is to trick you in an unexpected way. 
The question could seem to be about let’s say lambda syntax, but in real
it tests your knowledge about variable scoping. During taking tests you 
need to be very careful and stay focused all the time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
